A Guide to the Preston Family Papers, 1745-1915, Inventory
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
Special Collections, Wytheville Community College
Preston Family Papers 1745-1915, Inventory
Special Collections, Wytheville Community College
1968.2
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The estate of Frederick B. Kegley donated the Preston Family Papers to the Kegley Library of Wytheville Community College in 1968.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Preston family played a prominent role in settling and shaping the history of southwestern Virginia. The Preston Family Papers focus on the family of William Preston and his son John Preston.
Colonel William Preston, as he was known to his contemporaries and historians alike, was born in Newton Limaviddy in Londonderry County in northern Ireland on 25 December 1730 to John and Elizabeth Patton Preston. His family emigrated to Virginia in 1738 settling in Augusta County. After John Preston died in March 1748 .Elizabeth struggled to raise her one son William and four daughters Lettice, Margaret, Ann, and Mary.
In late 1749 the family moved closer to Elizabeth's brother. Colonel James Patton, a merchant, land agent, and militia colonel guided his young nephew in education and employment. Presbyterian minister John Craig tutored the young man in history, mathematics, and penmanship. William utilized this education as a secretary for his uncle. In time he also labored as a clerk for the Augusta County vestry which essentially controlled most county affairs.
William also surveyed land for his uncle who had received a large land grant, known as the Wood's River Grant in 1745. Although John Buchanan was Patton's principal surveyor, William Preston surveyed much of the land along the New River. By 1753, Preston had traveled extensively through Virginia and present day Maryland and Pennsylvania, surveying and keeping his uncle's accounts.
Tragedy struck in July 1755 when James Patton and several other settlers were massacred by Shawnee Indians. William, already a captain of rangers (militia) began a lifelong commitment to militia service after his uncle's death. He not only served throughout the French and Indian War (1754-1763) but also in the Revolutionary War. In the latter, he fought at the Battle of Guilford Courthouse in 1781 and proved valuable in protecting patriots against those settlers (Tories) loyal to England.
On 17 July 1761 William married Susanna Smith of Hanover Court House. Susanna, the daughter of carpenter Francis Smith, had also received extensive schooling from a Presbyterian cleric. The compatible couple had twelve children including sons John, Francis, William, John Patton, and Thomas Lewis. Their daughters included Elizabeth, Sarah, Ann, Susanna, Mary, Letitia, and Peggy Brown Preston.
After residing at Greenfield, Botetourt County for several years, Preston moved his large family to Montgomery County near present-day Blacksburg in 1774. There he build Smithfield, a home which housed many generations of Prestons.
In Montgomery County, William continued his career as a public servant. In Botetourt and Augusta counties, he had been a member of the House of Burgesses, coroner, escheator, and county surveyor. In Montgomery County, he served as a justice, sheriff, and surveyor. He also was chairman of the Committee of Safety for Fincastle County (Montgomery County was formed in 1777 out of Fincastle).
With his death on 28 June 1783, William Preston left his family considerable wealth in land, personal property, and slaves. His widow and eldest son carefully managed the estate and ensured that the large family continued to enjoy the prosperity their father had sown.
John Preston followed his father's model of public and military service. Born in May 1762, he married Mary Radford. Together they reared five children including William, John, Elizabeth, Susan and Sarah. In 1811 he married Elizabeth Ann Carrington Mayo of Richmond with whom he had one son Edward Carrington Preston.
Preston, known as General Preston, served as a captain, lieutenant colonel, and ultimately major general in the Virginia militia. He also worked as justice of the peace, surveyor, tax commissioner, highway overseer, and store merchant.
In statewide office, he served as delegate in 1783, 1791, and 1803 and senator from 1792 to 1800. John Preston was Treasurer of Virginia from 1809 to 1819. Unfortunately his later years were tinged with scandal. In 1820, the discovery of a deficiency in his accounts during his term as Treasurer caused the Preston family emotional and financial hardship. A deed of trust was entered against his property and soon his vast real estate holdings were sold to reimburse the state. Preston died in March 1827.
William's sons Francis and James Patton also led successful lives. Francis studied law at the College of William and Mary and lived in Abingdon and Saltville, Va. He married Sarah Buchanan Campbell, the daughter of General William Campbell, in January 1793. They had ten children. Francis served in the General Assembly, Congress, and was brigadier general in the Virginia Militia. He died in 1836.
James Patton Preston also studied law at William and Mary. He married Nancy Taylor of Norfolk and raised six children. Preston was surveyor, justice of the peace, and trustee for the town of Blacksburg. In 1802 he was elected to the Virginia State Senate. From 1816 to 1819 he served as Governor. At the time of his death in 1843, his estate was valued at $34,845.
Scope and Content
The Preston Family Papers chronicle the family, business, and political life of a prominent Southwest Virginia family. While offering glimpses of family life, the Papers primarily focus on land, business, legal, and political affairs of Colonel William Preston and his heirs.
Arrangement
The Papers are arranged in six series including correspondence, financial, legal, land, military, and miscellaneous records.
Arranged chronologically, correspondence (1746-1915, undated) comprises Series I. Letters dating from 1746 to 1783 generally discuss land plats, surveys, sale and transfers as well as business transactions between William Preston and George Skillern, William Campbell, Peter Hogg, Robert Carter, Flower Swift, and others. One 1783 letter from Robert Carter of Westmoreland County, Virginia exhorts Preston to deliver a runaway slave named Dick. Other letters to William Preston document his military service in the Revolutionary War.
Correspondence dating from 1784 to 1822 covers the land affairs, militia service, and political life of John Preston, son of William. Also included is a 1797 letter from Elizabeth Preston Madison bitterly denouncing vicious political attacks on her brothers Francis and John. Other letters document John Preston's tenure as Treasurer of Virginia.
Series II includes financial records (1745-1838, undated) of John Buchanan, James Patton, William Preston, John Preston and others. Bills and receipts (1745-1838) form the bulk of this series. Of especial interest, however, are account books kept by Lieutenant William B. Davis (1764) and John Preston (1817-1818).
Legal records (1754-1864, undated) are included in Series III. These records primarily focus on disputes over debts, land and rental of property as well as legal documentation of militia conduct.
A most important aspect of the Preston Papers is found in Series IV with land records (1746-1821, undated). Several survey books including one kept by Col. James Patton and William Preston, record surveys done for early settlers in the Roanoke Valley, New River Valley, and along the Holston River. Individual surveys are also found in this series; the land owner, surveyor, location, and date of survey, if known, is provided in the series listing.
Also included in this series are certificates (1781-1790) from commissioners of Montgomery County entitling various settlers to land. Many of these certificates, arranged chronologically, were transcribed by Mary B. Kegley. These transcriptions will be found in the front of each folder. Information on each certificate includes names of commissioner, land owner, location, and date of certificate issue.
Various agreements, receipts, memoranda, etc (1768-1821, undated) will also be found in Series IV.
Military records (1758-1807, undated) from the French and Indian War and Virginia militia comprise Series V. Included are provisional returns (1758-1761, undated) and a roll book for Capt. John Preston's company, 112th Regt., 19th Brig., Virginia Militia dated 1792. A pay roster (undated) for Capt. Robertson's company as well as a hand-drawn map of the Battle of First Manassas, 21 July 1861, are also found in this series.
Miscellaneous records (1821, undated) comprise Series VI. These records include account statements of Randolph Ross and the Treasury Department of Virginia and a newspaper photograph of William Preston's home, Greenfield, in Botetourt County.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence 1746-1915, undated
  - Correspondence 1746-1769
    - Meredith Helm to Colonel John Buchanan. 9 March 1746 (Drawer-folder 3:1.)
      1 p. Re: debt of Hugh Neal.
    - Alexander Mackie, Warwick, Va., to Colonel William Preston, at Fort Fauquier, [unknown]. 11 November 1758 (Drawer-folder 3:1.)
      1 p. Re: Preston's accounts. Torn.
    - George Skillern, Sharontown, [Va.], to Colonel William Preston, Greenfield, [Botetourt County, Va.]. 19 June 1764 (Drawer-folder 3:1.)
      1 p. Re: family, mares, and Indians on South River. Torn.
    - J [unknown] B [unknown] to [William Preston]. [unknown] 1769 (Drawer-folder 3:1.)
      2 p. Re: delinquent accounts. Includes memorandum for William Boyd.
  - Correspondence 1770-1774
    - Robert Harris Jr. to Colonel William Preston. 20 [illegible] 1770 (Drawer-folder 3:2)
      1 p. Faded, torn.
    - William Campbell, South River, [unknown], to [William Preston]. 10 March 1772 (Drawer-folder 3:2)
      7 p. Re: land purchased by Patrick Campbell and Thomas Steel. Also the improper conduct of Chevalier M[-o-s-n].
    - Reverend Adam Smyth, Staunton, Va. to Colonel William Preston, Botetourt, Va. 1 June 1772 (Drawer-folder 3:2)
      2 p. Re: Smyth's desired appointment to parish of Botetourt County.
    - Thomas Prosser to [William Preston]. 15 January 1773 (Drawer-folder 3:2)
      1 p. Re: sale of land of John Howard in Botetourt County.
    - Richard Crump, Manchester, Va. to Colonel William Preston. 8 October 1773 (Drawer-folder 3:2)
      2 p. Re: supply of hemp and money to Crump by Preston.
    - John Hawkins to [William Preston]. 26 January 1774. 1 p. Re: money owed by Preston to Hawkins. (Drawer-folder 3:2)
    - Peter Hog, Staunton, Va. to William Preston. 15 March 1774 (Drawer-folder 3:2)
      1 p. Re: land in Fincastle County.
    - James Gilmer, Fincastle, Va. to Colonel William Preston. 12 October 1774 (Drawer-folder 3:2)
      2 p. Re: problems with cattle driving.
  - Correspondence 1775-1779
    - James Allen, Middle River, Va. to Colonel William Preston, Fincastle, Va. 25 February 1775 (Drawer-folder 3:3.)
      4 p. Re: disposition of land of his deceased brother John.
    - James Hughes and [unknown] Swan, Elizabeth Town, Md. to William Preston. 14 July 1775 (Drawer-folder 3:3.)
      1 p. Re: land warrant of Thomas Price. Cellophane taped.
    - James Trimble to Colonel William Preston. 28 March 1771 (Drawer-folder 3:3.)
      1 p. Re: land. On reverse is receipt from Michael Doughearty to William Preston. 3 April 1778
    - James Thompson to Col. William Preston, Montgomery County, Va. 15 December 1779 (Drawer-folder 3:3.)
      1 p. Re: purchase of salt from Robert Preston.
  - Correspondence 1780-1783
    - George May to William Preston, Montgomery County, Va. 7 February 1780 (Drawer-folder 3:4.)
      1 p. Re: land survey.
    - George Skillern, Framed House, Botetourt, Va. to William Preston. 4 March 1780. 3 p. Re: land surveyed on fork of Elkhorn River. (Drawer-folder 3:4.)
    - George Skillern to Col. William Preston, Montgomery, Va. 7 November 1780 (Drawer-folder 3:4.)
      1 p. Re: recruitment of volunteer troops. Cellophane taped.
    - Charles Floyd to Col. William Preston, Montgomery County, Va. [unknown] 1780 (Drawer-folder 3:4.)
      Re: land on Potts Creek [Alleghany County, Va.].
    - Robert Carter, Westmoreland County, Va. to William Preston, Montgomery County, Va. 16 April 1782 (Drawer-folder 3:4.)
      1 p. Re: return of runaway slave.
    - John Reyburn to William Preston, Drapers Meadow, Va. 27 July 1782 (Drawer-folder 3:4.)
      1 p. Re: money owned to William Preston.
    - Alexander Baine to William Preston. 6 September 1782 (Drawer-folder 3:4.)
      1 p. Re: land plat.
    - Col. John Taylor to William Preston. 3 December 1782 (Drawer-folder 3:4.)
      3 p. Re: land. Fragment, torn, and ink faded.
    - [Flower Swift] to William Preston. 24 January 1783 (Drawer-folder 3:4.)
      1 p. Re: tax collected.
  - Correspondence 1784-1789
    - Andrew Boyd to William Thompson. 25 August 1784 (Drawer-folder 3:5.)
      1 p. Re: request for bond of James Thompson due to executors of Col. Patton.
    - John Wylie to John Preston, Surveyor, Montgomery County, Va. 17 May 1786 (Drawer-folder 3:5.)
      1 p. Re: land.
    - Richard Chapman to John Preston. 29 September 1786 (Drawer-folder 3:5.)
      1 p. Re: land released to [illegible] Purdue.
    - George Peery to John Preston. 26 November 1786 (Drawer-folder 3:5.)
      1 p. Re: signing over of land to John Davidson.
    - T. Walker to John Preston, Montgomery County, Va. 8 December 1787 (Drawer-folder 3:5.)
      1 p. Re: land warrant.
    - John Poage, Augusta County, Va. to John Preston, Surveyor, Montgomery County, Va. 5 January 1788 (Drawer-folder 3:5.)
      1 p. Re: request by Francis Green for land patent "lodged" with William Preston 15 years previous.
    - Sam Park to John Preston. 8 September 1788 (Drawer-folder 3:5.)
    - Alexander Page to Capt. John Preston. 18 September 1789 (Drawer-folder 3:5.)
      1 p. Re: land On same page John Pruet to John Preston, Surveyor, Montgomery County, Va. 19 September 1789. 1 p. Also on same page are notes by John Carper. Transcript by Mary B. Kegley.
  - Correspondence 1790-1799
    - John Thompson to William Thompson, Botetourt, Va. 4 March 1790 (Drawer-folder 3:6.)
      1 p. Re: request for stone and timber.
    - Jesse Robinet to Francis Preston. 13 March 1790 (Drawer-folder 3:6.)
      1 p. Re: land transfer to Joseph Coch [Couch].
    - Robert Crockett to W. [Contractor]. 23 June 1792 (Drawer-folder 3:6.)
      1 p. Re: request for rations for militia.
    - James Patton Preston to John Preston. 30 October 1796 (Drawer-folder 3:6.)
      1 p.
    - A. Lewis to John Preston. 30 October 1796 (Drawer-folder 3:6.)
    - Elizabeth Preston Madison, Saltworks, [Saltville], Va. to John Preston. 27 February 1797 (Drawer-folder 3:6.)
      3 p. Re: political attacks on John and Francis Preston.
    - John Craig to Gen. John Preston, Smithfield, Montgomery County, Va. 9 June 1799 (Drawer-folder 3:6.)
      1 p. Re: heartshorn [hartshorn or ammonia carbonate] and instructions for its medicinal use.
  - Correspondence 1801-1815
    - David Wade to Gen. John Preston. 25 October 1801 (Drawer-folder 3:7.)
      1 p. Re: money owed to Preston.
    - James McDowell, Rockbridge County, Va. to Gen. John Preston, Montgomery County, Va. 24 August 1802 (Drawer-folder 3:7.)
      1p. Re: McDowell's trip to Kentucky.
    - Robert Ewing to Capt. John Preston, Montgomery County, Va. 12 November 1805 (Drawer-folder 3:7.)
      Re: the filing of plat of Mr. Shannon.
    - James McDowell, Fairfield, Rockbridge County, Va. to Gen. John Preston, Richmond, Va. 9 January 1809 (Drawer-folder 3:7.)
      2 p. Re: the selling price of iron, flour and whiskey in Richmond. Also discusses Preston's possible appointment in the Office of the Treasury.
    - Creed Taylor, Richmond, Va. to Gen. John Preston, Richmond, Va. 12 November 1811 (Drawer-folder 3:7.)
      Re: recommendation for John Otey for employment in Office of Treasury.
    - Chapman Johnson, Staunton, Va. to Gen. John Preston, Richmond, Va. 15 November 1815 (Drawer-folder 3:7.)
      1 p. Re: conditioned decree in case of John [Jordan] of Rockbridge against Trustees of Ann Smith Academy.
  - Correspondence 1817-1915
    - Reverend Samuel Houston, Natural Bridge, Va. to Gen. John Preston, Richmond, Va. 8 March 1817 (Drawer-folder 3:8.)
      2 p. Re: education of Preston's son John. Also Houston's desire for more educational opportunities for youth of Virginia. Torn.
    - William Wirt, Washington, D. C. to Gen. John Preston, Richmond, Va. 11 June 1818 (Drawer-folder 3:8.)
      Re: copy of land grant. Torn, mended with cellophane tape.
    - William Fleming, Summerville, [unknown] to Gen. John Preston, Treasurer of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 27 November 1818 (Drawer-folder 3:8.)
      1 p. Re: "money matter."
    - Francis Preston, Abingdon, Va. to Gen. John Preston, near Fincastle, Va. 14 March 1822 (Drawer-folder 3:8.)
      3 p. Re: Francis' dim prospect of purchasing "Horseshoe" land and power of attorney document to John Robertson
    - Thomas B. Robertson, Eastville, Va. to Alfred Preston, [Greenfield, Botetourt County, Va.]. 2-Mar-15 (Drawer-folder 3:8.)
      1 p. Re: request for family Bible of Betsie Robertson.
  - Correspondence undated
    - F. Smith to Captain Thomas Quirk. N.d. [before Quirk's death in 1808] (Drawer-folder 3:9.)
      1 p. Re: money owed by Smith to Quirk.
    - Thomas [unknown], Franklin County, Va. to [John Preston], Surveyor of Montgomery County, Va. N.d (Drawer-folder 3:9.)
      1 p. Re: land on Peach Bottom Creek on which he had first claim. Torn, fragment.
    - Thomas Madison to John Green and [unknown] Thomas. N.d (Drawer-folder 3:9.)
      1 p. Re: 20 pound settlement with William Preston. Notation on reverse probably by William Preston.
    - [Unknown] to W[unknown] P[unknown]. N.d (Drawer-folder 3:9.)
      1 p. regarding land contract between Col. James Patton and [James] Burk. Transcript by Mary B. Kegley. Fragment.
- Series II Financial Records, 1745-1838, undated
  - Financial Records - Bills and Receipts 1745-1759 (Drawer-folder 3:1.)
    14 items.
  - Financial Records - Bills and Receipts 1760-1763 (Drawer-folder 3:2.)
    14 items
  - Financial Records - Bills and Receipts 1764-1768 (Drawer-folder 3:3.)
    9 items
  - Financial Records - Bills and Receipts 1771-1778 (Drawer-folder 3:4.)
  - Financial Records - Bills and Receipts 1780-1789 (Drawer-folder 3:5.)
  - Financial Records - Bills and Receipts 1790-1799 (Drawer-folder 3:6.)
    7 items
  - Financial Records - Bills and Receipts 1805-1838 (Drawer-folder 3:7.)
    10 items
  - Financial Records - Bills and Receipts undated (Drawer-folder 3:8.)
    15 items
  - Financial Records - Account Book 1761-1762 (Drawer-folder 3:9.)
  - Financial Records - Account Book Name Index 1764 (Drawer-folder 3:10.)
    Kept by Lt. William B. Davis. Dated on front 25 September and 2 October 1764.
  - Financial Records - Account Book 1817-1818. (Drawer-folder 3:11.)
    Account book kept by John Preston which records cash advances, transactions with the Bank of Virginia, family expenses, purchase of a slave, farming expenses, etc.
  - Financial Records - Account Book undated. (Drawer-folder 3:12.)
    Account book which has written on front page "An acct of the sale of the estate of David Miller (deceased)." Fragment.
  - Financial Records - Account Book Name Indices undated. (Drawer-folder 3:13.)
    2 items. One has on front page written "Alphabett for Small Account Book No. 7." and "Smithfield."
- Series III: Legal Records, 1754-1864, undated
  - Legal Records 1754 - 1778. (Drawer-folder 3:1.)
    5 items. Folder includes complaints, contracts, memorandum of agreement, and agreement between William Preston and Joseph Culton, Andrew Boyd, William Thompson, Benjamin Estiel, George Skillern, Skidmore Munsey, Joseph Montgomery, and Henry Patton.
  - Legal Records 1780-1796. (Drawer-folder 3:2.)
    4 items. Folder includes agreement, arbitration and judgment of complaint, power of attorney, and certification of court for James Novell, John Dudot, Thomas Tate, David Carr, John Breckinridge, Jane Ealy, Thomas Ealy, John Preston.
  - Legal Records 1805-1864, undated. (Drawer-folder 3:3.)
    7 items. Folder includes summons, petition, affidavit, depositions and judgments for John Preston, Dr. R. E. Bouldin, Alfred T. Dillard, William Thompson, John Robinson, and James Whitten.
- Series IV: Land Records, 1746-1821, undated
  - Land and Survey Book. James Patton 1752 (Drawer-folder 3:1.)
    Land and survey book kept by Col. James Patton and William Preston. Pages [1-5] records land transactions of James Patton; pages [18-100, 105-117] record surveys made by William Preston in 1752 along Calfpasture, Cowpasture, and Roanoke rivers.
  - Land and Survey Book. James Patton 1752 - (Drawer-folder 3:2.)
    Photocopy. Photocopy of book in Folder 1.
  - Survey book 1754-1763. (Drawer-folder 3:3.)
    Survey book by [unknown] records surveys of lands near Calfpasture, Catawba, James, and Roanoke Rivers.
  - Survey book 1783 (Drawer-folder 3:4.)
    Survey book kept by [unknown] of surveys in Montgomery County, Pulaski County, and Roanoke County near New River, Back Creek, Walker's Creek, and Wolf Creek.
  - Survey book 1783-1788. (Drawer-folder 3:5.)
    Survey book kept by John Taylor who recorded surveys near East River, Indian Creek, Wolf Creek, Walkers Creek, and New River.
  - Survey book 1770-1772. (Drawer-folder 3:6.)
    Survey book kept by [unknown] surveyor which records charges and payments received for surveying. Book gives date and name of land owner.
  - Survey Account Book - Fragments 1767-1777. (Drawer-folder 3:7.)
    Survey account book fragments from 1767, 1770, 1772, and 1776-1777 which record charges and payments received for surveying. Information given includes date and name of land owner.
  - Surveys 1746-1769. (Drawer-folder 3:8.)
    4 items. Folder includes surveys for Marcus Calamer on Middle Fork of Indian River 1746; William Hutchinson, Samuel Thompson, John Marten, and Erick bright in 1755; John Weylie Sr. on east side of New River, 1769
  - Surveys 1780-1789. (Drawer-folder 3:9.)
    6 items. Folder includes surveys for Abraham Goad on Burk Fork, 1783; John Henderson near confluence of Great Kanawha, 1786; Peter Groseclose on North Fork of Holston River, 1787; Samuel McCraw on Back Creek, 1787; James Cooley on New River, 1788; and John Vansel on south side of Little River, 1789.
  - Surveys 1790-1794, undated. (Drawer-folder 3:10.)
    Folder includes surveys for Matthew Lindsey on Sally Run, 1790; Joseph Landon on Roanoke River, 1790; John Smith in 1791; William and John Haven on east side of New River, 1794; and John Ogle on Big Reed Island Creek, n.d.
  - Commissioners Certificates 1791 (Drawer-folder 3:11.)
    Folder includes certificates for James Hill on Holston River in Washington County; Rodger Oats on Cripple Creek in Montgomery County; William Engledove on Walkers Creek in Montgomery County; Francis Kincannon on South Fork of Holston in Montgomery County; and John Ross on north side of Clinch River in Washington County.
  - Commissioners Certificates 1782-1790. (Drawer-folder 3:12.)